Guide to the Nan Netherton Reston history collection, 1962-1989
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Nan Netherton Northern Virginia history collection
1962-1989
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Nan Netherton, 1925-2003
C0147
12 linear feet 20 boxes (6 boxes)
The Nan Netherton Northern Virginia history collection contains Netherton's research and notes from her book "Reston: A New Town in the Old Dominion: A Pictorial History" (1989), as well as "Arlington County in Virginia: A Pictorial History" (1987) and "Fairfax County in Virginia: A Pictorial History," coauthored with Ross Netherton. Within the collection there are outlines for chapters, the copies of all the illustrations for the book, and the sources that Nan Netherton used during the writing process. The collection also contains oral histories, reports, brochures, photographs, executive budgets, and newsletters on historic sites in Northern Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Nan Netherton on November 16, 1989 and by Nan and Ross Netherton in 2001, 2002, and 2007.
Biographical Information
Nan Netherton was an author and historian who wrote books about the origins, growth and customs of communities in Northern Virginia. The books include pictorial and narrative histories of a dozen Virginia counties. Some of the books that she wrote are "Fairfax County Virginia: A History" (1978), "Clifton: Brigadoon in Virginia" (1980), and "Books and Beyond: Fairfax County Public Library's First Fifty Years" (1990). She died on June 9, 2003 in Arlington, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Nan Netherton Northern Virginia history collection contains Netherton's research and notes from her book "Reston: A New Town in the Old Dominion: A Pictorial History" (1989), as well as "Arlington County in Virginia: A Pictorial History" (1987) and "Fairfax County in Virginia: A Pictorial History," coauthored with Ross Netherton. Within the collection there are outlines for chapters, the copies of all the illustrations for the book, and the sources that Nan Netherton used during the writing process. The collection also contains oral histories, reports, brochures, photographs, executive budgets, and newsletters on historic sites in Northern Virginia.
Materials include brochures on the Woodlawn Plantation and Calvin Run Mill; comprehensive reports on plans for the Fairfax County Park Authority; audio tapes and transcripts of interviews with curators and historical preservationists, including an interview with former Gunston Hall curator Benny Brown and another with former Reston land developer Robert E. Simon, Jr.; newsclippings and an essay on Gunston Hall and a pamphlet calling for public opposition to the cutting of funding for Gunston Hall and the privatization of the Virginia Museum of Natural History; and eight boxes of images used in Netherton's pictorial histories of Fairfax and Arlington.
Series one is comprised of Nan Netherton's writings. The documents in this series are the outlines for her book in chapter format. There are ten chapters in order in the series. The books begins with the founding of Fairfax and ends with Reston, following the take over by the Gulf Oil Coporation in the late 1960s.
Series two contains the illustrations from Nan Netherton's book. Like the chapters, the illustrations are in order with pages numbers on the folders that correspond with the page numbers they would be placed in the book. Some of the illustrations are copies of documents from the 18th and 19th centuries. There are also slides and photographs from the 1960s and 1980s.
Series three is a general series of the sources that Nan Netherton used in her research. The series is organized in alphabetical order. The sources in this series are the more contemporary sources that deal primarily with Reston from the 1960s to the 1980s. Some of the sources include directories and maps from the Reston area.
Arrangement
Organized into three series.
Series 1: Writings, 1960s-1980s (Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Illustrations, 1960s-1980s (Boxes 2-4)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1960s-1980s (Boxes 4-6)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
The Special Collections and Archives also holds the Planned Community Archives and other personal papers and organizational records that document Reston, Virginia, and other planned communities.
Index Terms
Persons:
Netherton, Nan.
Geographical Names:
Fairfax County (Va.)--History.; Reston (Va.)--History.
Subjects:
Housing--Virginia--Reston.; Planned communities--Virginia--Reston.
Contents List
- Series 1: Writings, 1960s-1980s (1.5 boxes)
  The documents in this series are the outlines for her book in chapter formate. There are ten chapters in order in the series which outlines the history of Reston beginning with the founding of Fairfax County.
  - Reston Study: First Increment, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    172.1
  - Chapter 1: Reston Great Falls Manor, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    172.2
  - Chapter 2: Thornton, (1852-1886), 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    172.3
  - Chapter 3: Wiehle Traum, (1886-1908), 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    172.4
  - Chapter 4: Dr. Hugh B. Hutchison, (1908-1927), 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    172.5
  - Chapter 5: Bowmans and Sunset Hills, (1927-1961), 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    172.6
  - Chapter 6: Robert E. Sunon, Jr. and "Reston", (1961-1967), 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    172.7
  - Chapter 7: A Dream Becomes a Nightmare, (1967), 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 8)
    172.8
  - Chapter 8: Reston-Gulf, (1967-1978), 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    172.9
  - Chapter 8: Reston-Gulf, (1967-1978), 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    172.10
  - Chapter 9: Mobilization, (1978-1989), 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 11)
    173.1
  - Chapter 9: Mobilization, (1978-1989), 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 1)
    173.2
  - Chapter 9: Mobilization, (1978-1989), 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 2)
    173.3
  - Chapter 10: New Designs for Living, 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 3)
    173.4
  - Chapter 10: New Designs for Living, 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    173.5
  - Chapters 1-6, 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 5)
    12.11
  - Chapter 7-11, 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 6)
    12.12
  - Notes and Apprendixes, Index, 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 7)
    12.13
- Series 2: Illustrations, 1960s-1980s (2 boxes)
  Series two is the illustrations from Nan Netherton's book. The illustrations are in the order they appear in the book with page numbers. Included are slides, photocopies and photographs.
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.5-7, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 8)
    175.1
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.8, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 9)
    175.2
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.15, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 10)
    175.3
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.16, 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 11)
    175.4
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.20-22, (1802), 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 12)
    175.6
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.25, (1860), 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 13)
    175.7
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.28, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 14)
    175.9
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.31-32, (1892), 1960s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 1)
    175.10
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.44-46, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    175.14
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.49-51, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    175.15
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.53-55, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 4)
    175.16
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.57-61, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    175.17
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.63-65, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 6)
    175.18
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.67-69, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    175.19
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.70-75, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 8)
    175.20
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.77-79, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 9)
    175.21
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.81-83, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 10)
    175.22
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.85, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 11)
    175.23
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.91-93, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 12)
    175.24
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.95-99, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 13)
    175.25
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.101-107, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 14)
    175.26
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.108-111, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    175.27
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.116-117, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 16)
    176.2
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.118-121, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    176.3
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.123-125, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    176.4
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.132-135, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    176.6
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.136-138, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    176.7
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.141-143, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    176.8
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.144-147, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    176.9
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.148-151, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 23)
    176.10
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.152-155, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    176.11
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.156-158, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 25)
    176.12
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.163-165, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 26)
    176.13
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.167-169, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    176.14
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.171-173, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    176.15
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.174-177, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    176.16
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.178, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    176.17
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.180-183, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    176.18
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.184-186, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    176.19
  - Reston Book Illustrations p.187-190, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    176.20
  - Reston Book Illustrations Negatives, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 6)
    176.21
- Series 3: Subject A-Z, 1960s-1980s (2.5 boxes)
  This series is organized in alphabetical order. The documents in this series are the sources from Netherton's book and are the contemporary sources that deal primarily with Reston from the 1960s to the 1980s.
  - "A Place Called Reston", 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    179.4
  - Appendix-reston Design Awards, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    174.9
  - Business Directory, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    179.6
  - Bylaws of the Reston Homeowner Association, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    177.4
  - Correspondence and Notes, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    178.1
  - Directory of Business and INdustry, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    179.5
  - "Dispersing Population" by James L. Sundquist, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    179.1
  - Greater Reston Arts Center, Incorporated, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 14)
    178.4
  - Handbook, Reston Residents, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    177.8
  - Homeowners Associations in Reston, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    177.1
  - Houe Beautiful "Best Small House", 1984 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    178.2
  - Information on "The Builders' House" Correspondence, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Maps of Washington D.C., 1980s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    178.7
  - "Naturescaping: Your Guide to Reforestation and Meadowmaking", 1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    177.6
  - Newsletter: "Reston Realtor Alert", 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    178.5
  - Northern Virginia Legal Directory, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    179.3
  - Notes, 1981-1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    12.10
  - Publicity and Newsclippings, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    177.10
  - Program Budget for the Reston Homeowners Association, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    177.5
  - Promotional Material-Reston Realtors, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    178.8
  - Robert E. Simon Letter, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    13.9
  - Reston Appendix, 1960s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 11)
    174.5
  - Reston Business Directory, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    179.2
  - Reston Chapter Notes, 1960s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 13)
    174.8
  - "Reston Express Bus", 1969 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    177.7
  - Reston Geographic Society, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    178.10
  - Reston-List of Sources, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    174.7
  - Reston Maps, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    174.3
  - Restonian Magazine, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    178.6
  - Reston Neighborhoods, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    178.9
    - Reston Neighborhoods, 1989; 1.
  - Reston Music, 1960s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 2)
    174.1
  - Reston Promotional Material, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Reston 1970-1975"-Report for Reston Homeowners Association (Box 6, Folder 4)
    177.3
  - Reston Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Note Paper, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    174.2
  - Role and Structure-Report, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    177.2
  - Space Station Program Offices in Reston, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    178.11
  - Updates, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    174.6
  - Urban Land Magazine, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    177.9